Felipe Schmidt Fonseca

• Home: Boxhagener Strasse 68, 10245, Berlin, Germany

Email: felipefonseca@gmail.com **Phone:** (+49) 1794160380

Date of birth: 26/08/1978 Nationality: Brazilian

ABOUT ME

I am Dr. Felipe Schmidt Fonseca, an experienced Berlin-based Brazilian advocate for social-environmental innovation and free/open-source technologies turned researcher. I am the founder of Reuse City studio and a co-creator of semente, a toolkit for community projects; as well as the co-founder and lead articulator of the Tropixel network; and an active member of organisations such as GIG and Circular Berlin.

EDUCATION AND TRAIN-ING

[27/07/2019 - 21/09/2023] PhD - School of Art, Design and Social Sciences

Northumbria University

City: Newcastle-upon-Tyne | Country: United Kingdom | Field(s) of study: Communic ation Design | Thesis: Generous Cities - commons-oriented systems for the reuse of excess materials in cities

My PhD investigation was part of a doctoral training project called OpenDoTT, in partnership with a consortium of organisations led by Mozilla Foundation. It was funded by the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme under the Marie Skłodowska-Curie programme.

Training modules included:

- · Design Research
- Open Leadership
- Prototyping with Open-Source Hardware
- · Privacy by Design
- · Policy-making

[01/02/2012 - 25/03/2014]

MA Scientific and Cultural Diffusion

Labjor, UNICAMP

City: Campinas | Country: Brazil | | Thesis: REDE/LABS - Laboratórios Experimentais em Rede ("Networked Experimental Labs")

[08/02/2001 - 26/01/2007]

BA Corporate Communications Management

Universidade Anhembi Morumbi

City: São Paulo | Country: Brazil |

WORK EXPERIENCE

[01/12/2024 - Current] Researcher - Circular Society

Global Innovation Gathering e.V.

City: Berlin | **Country:** Germany

Creating and developing projects on social and environmental approaches to the circular economy.

[09/2024 – Current] **Founder**

Reuse City

City: Berlin | **Country:** Germany

Reuse City is a studio dedicated to applied research, service design and technology development in the fields of circular economy, right to repair, and zero waste policy.

[01/2023 - Current] Freelance Consultant

City: Berlin | **Country:** Germany

Developing independent research and projects such as:

- Semente An interactive method to create and re-generate community-based initiatives (2022-). Funded by the University of Bristol.
- ALGO-Lab Co-design lab about algorithmic discrimination and games in Brazil (2023). Partnership between GIG and the University of Bristol.
- On the Exactitude of Maps Artwork and situated research on implications of geospatial data in contemporary society (2023). Part of the CODE program of Impakt (Utrecht), Transmediale (Berlin) and CPDP (Brussels).
- Scaling Distributed Manufacturing in the Global South. Commissioned by UK's Frontier Tech Hub (2023).
- Distributed Design Mentor Scheme (2023-).

[01/06/2013 – Current] Founder, Curator and Executive Producer

Tropixel

City: Ubatuba | Country: Brazil

I have organised 5 editions of Tropixel, each in a different format.

Festival and activity platform on arts, science, technology and society (Ubatuba, SP, Brazil).

[27/07/2019 - 27/07/2022] Marie Curie Early Stage Researcher / PhD candidate

Northumbria University / Dundee University / Mozilla Foundation

Country: United Kingdom

OpenDoTT was "a PhD programme to explore how to build a more open, secure, and trustworthy Internet of Things". The project received funding from the European Union's Horizon 2020 Marie-Skłodowska-Curie research and innovation programme.

My research topic in the programme was "Smart Cities". My thesis explores the theme "Waste Prevention and Generous Cities".

[01/05/2022 – 31/07/2022] **Project manager, semente**

Instituto Neos

City: Ubatuba | **Country:** Brazil

Semente co-designed participatory methods to build community-based digital inclusion projects.

Project funded by the University of Bristol.

[01/08/2021 - 30/11/2021]

Brazil team co-lead, Tales of Care and Repair

Instituto Cabra

City: Casa Branca | Country: Brazil

Tales of Care and Repair promoted collaboration between England, India and Brazil about repair culture, collecting one thousand stories of repairs from those countries, organising local and international seminars and editing repair declarations for each context.

Project funded by the British Council's Creative Commissions programme for COP-26.

[01/07/2021 – 30/11/2021] **Project owner, fonte.wiki**

Instituto Neos

City: Ubatuba | **Country:** Brazil

fonte.wiki is an open-source repository of open educational resources about digital policies in Brazil.

Project funded by the Bristol Digital Futures Institute, in cooperation with the University of Bristol

[01/03/2021 - 01/07/2021]

Project owner, ID21

Instituto Neos

City: Ubatuba | Country: Brazil

ID21 interviewed leaders of Brazilian digital inclusion projects and elaborated a report on how to navigate their current concerns and possibilities.

Project funded by the University of Bristol's Impact Acceleration Account, in cooperation with the University of Bristol.

[01/03/2017 – 31/10/2019] Consultant, Transversalidade da Memória

Instituto Itaú Cultural

City: São Paulo | Country: Brazil

Co-creation and implementation of Transversalidade da Memória, a programme promoting the digitisation of the department of Documentation and Archives of the Institute and creating a community of practice across organisations in Brazil.

[01/09/2017 - 30/06/2019]

User Community Manager, Subutai Platform

OptDyn, LLC

City: New Castle, DE | **Country:** United States

Managing community engagement and open documentation for the open source software Subutai.

[01/09/2015 - 01/10/2019] Head of Digital and Urban Cultures

Municipal Advisory Board on Public Policy for Culture

City: Ubatuba | **Country:** Brazil

Served two terms as an elected member of the cultural policy board.

Leader of the Working Group responsible for Ubatuba Municipality's 10-year Cultural Policy Plan.

[01/04/2014 - 30/06/2019] Founder

ninho co-working space

City: Ubatuba | Country: Brazil

ninho co-working space and center of science and culture.

[01/02/2010 - 30/06/2019]

Founder

UbaLab

City: Ubatuba | Country: Brazil

Head of UbaLab Experimental Digital Culture Lab.

Consultancy, educational programmes, experimental initiatives, community-building.

[01/08/2018 – 31/10/2018] **Co-curator – AEI (Electronic Indigenous Art)**

Associação Thydewá

City: Olivença | **Country:** Brazil

Artistic residence programme pairing electronic artists and indigenous communities in north-east Brazil.

[15/01/2018 – 10/04/2018] **Research Assistant, Tainacan**

MediaLab Goiânia, Universidade de Goiás

City: Goiânia | Country: Brazil

Research topic: Tainacan – free / open source software for digital archives.

[01/03/2015 – 17/03/2017] Research Assistant, Ciência Aberta Ubatuba

IBICT

City: Rio de Janeiro | **Country:** Brazil

Participatory Action Research project investigating Open and Collaborative Science and

Development.

Coordinating activities developed in Ubatuba, SP, Brazil.

Project funded by OCSDNet / IDRC | CRDI (Canada).

[01/10/2016 - 05/11/2016] Junior Fellow, DCRL (Digital Cultures Research Lab)

Leuphana University

City: Lüneburg | **Country:** Germany

Research topic: Design and Repair.

[01/09/2016 - 30/09/2016]

Researcher in Residence, (s)lowtech

PiNG Association

City: Nantes | **Country:** France

Atelier Partagé du Breil/ Plateforme C.

Research topic: Transformation of Matter / Repair and Reuse.

Consultant

Brazilian Culture Ministry

City: Brasília | Country: Brazil

Funded by the Brazilian Ministry of Culture and UNDP.

Commissioned reports about Policies for Experimental Digital Culture (2011) and Creative Experimental Arrangements on Digital Culture (2015).

[01/12/2014 - 16/12/2014] **Designer in Residence**

Virginia Commonwealth University Qatar

City: Doha | Country: Qatar

Working with 10 MFA Students to experiment with Repair Culture.

[01/02/2014 – 31/07/2014] **Part-time teacher, MIN**

Escola Técnica Tancredo Neves

City: Ubatuba | **Country:** Brazil

Teaching hardware and computer repair to 14-15 year olds.

[01/09/2006 - 01/06/2013] **Founder / Articulator**

Bricolabs network

Country: Brazil

Weaving an international community of makers, thinkers, researchers and activists around the idea of generic infrastructures, open source and change.

[01/01/2012 – 30/04/2012] **Commissioned writer, REDE//LABS**

CCE/AECID (Spanish Cultural Center / International Cooperation and Development Agency)

City: São Paulo | Country: Brazil

Series of articles and videos about experimental laboratories.

[01/07/2012 - 31/07/2012]

Artist in residence, OCA Digital

Thydewá

City: Olivença | Country: Brazil

Workshops and experimentation with digital maps and first peoples communities.

[08/2012 - 09/2012]

Researcher

Inventta

City: Campinas | Country: Brazil

Research on WEEE and potential solutions - part of a study commissioned by the Brazilian Ministry of Industry and Commerce.

[01/12/2002 - 01/12/2012] **Founder**

MetaReciclagem

City: São Paulo | Country: Brazil

A nationwide network of community-based laboratories for the refurbishment of discarded electronics.

MetaReciclagem was supported by numerous agencies and organisations and received awards in Brazil and abroad.

[01/12/2011 - 15/12/2011]

Curator and executive producer, LabX

Festival CulturaDigital.Br

City: Rio de Janeiro | Country: Brazil

Head of the experimental laboratory during the Festival, featuring 15 artists from 7 countries.

[01/06/2003 – 30/04/2007] **Articulator**

Brazilian Culture Ministry

City: Brasília | Country: Brazil

Leading roles in Articuladores, the group responsible for the concept and implementation of the Digital Culture strategy for the Cultura Viva / Pontos de Cultura programme, which deployed free and open source media production studios in hundreds of grassroots cultural centres from all regions of Brazil.

LANGUAGE SKILLS

Mother tongue(s): Portuguese

Other language(s):

English

LISTENING C2 READING C2 WRITING C1

SPOKEN PRODUCTION C1 SPOKEN INTERACTION C1

Spanish

LISTENING B2 READING C1 WRITING B1

SPOKEN PRODUCTION B1 SPOKEN INTERACTION B2

German

LISTENING B1 READING B2 WRITING B1

SPOKEN PRODUCTION B1 SPOKEN INTERACTION B1

Levels: A1 and A2: Basic user; B1 and B2: Independent user; C1 and C2: Proficient user